In the last lecture we adjusted to logo to look good in both the toolbar and the sideDrawer,
Son dersimizde hem ara ubuunda hem de Deeside ekmecesinde iyi grnmesi iin logoya ayarladk.
now let's adjust navigation items too. Right now, negation items especially the single items here
imdi navigasyon elerini imdi ve sonra negatif eleri okumak zere ayarlayalm, zellikle burada
are only styled to look good on desktop devices.
tek eler masast cihazlarda iyi grnmeye balyor.
That's of course the issue, on mobile devices,
Tabii ki mobil cihazlardaki mesele bu.
we still have that desktop look
O masast grnmn kaldrdk.
but instead I want to have some items which simply sit beneath each other and which are not having
Ancak bunun yerine, sadece birbirinin altna oturup altta bu snr olmayan
this border at the bottom and so on.
baka elere sahip olmak istemektedirler.
So we have to adjust the navigation items and it will do this with media queries in the navigation
ve bunu medya sorgularyla yapacaz ve gezinme eleri bizi dosya olarak gryor.
items css file.
Dolaysyla, gezinme elerini ayarlamalyz
So here, I want to write this in a mobile first way so my base classes should be for mobile devices and
Dolaysyla, bunu mobil bir yolla ilk defa yazmak istiyorum, bylece temel snflarm mobil cihazlar iin olmaldr ve daha
then I'll add media queries to make it look good on bigger devices too.
sonra byk cihazlarda da iyi grnmesi iin medya sorular ekleyeceim.
So to achieve this, let's first of all add this desktop device media queries or the single media
Bu nedenle, nce bu masastne Wise medya sorgularn ekleyelim veya tek medya kartp aslnda
query it actually is. I'll write media and then min-width, for me the cut off point here will be 500px
tm doru medyay alp, sonra da menwith'i benim iin kesmek iin 500 piksel yapalm.
but of course you can choose a different one. I'll now
Ancak elbette u anda farkl bir seim yapabilirsiniz.
copy all the existing css classes into that media query because we did write for desktop before
Mevcut Seer'in snflarn tm o medyaya Querrey'ye kopyalayn nk daha nce masast iin yazdk.
so we definitely want to use these classes for broader devices and now I want to adjust these base classes
iin kesinlikle kullanmak istiyoruz ve imdi bu temel snflar mobil cihazlarda iyi grnecek ekilde ayarlamak istiyoruz.
to look good on mobile.
Dolaysyla, bu snflar daha geni cihazlar
This for example includes to have a margin of 10px from top and bottom and zero to top and right
Bu, rnein, stten ve alttan 10 piksel, stten ve saa sfr olmak zere bir kenar boluuna sahip olmay ierir.
so there is some spacing between my links.
Dolaysyla, postalar arasnda biraz boluk var.
I also want to set the width now to 100% but not the height, the height should be only taking the
Ayrca imdi genilii% 100 olarak ayarlamak istiyorum ancak gizlenecek ykseklie deil yalnzca bir metin perspektifinden
height it needs from a text perspective and the display doesn't have to be flex, the display can be block
ihtiya duyduu ykseklii alyor olmal ve ekrann burada esnek olmas iin ekran
here
bloklanabilir.
and I also don't need align-items for that reason.
Ayrca bu nedenle bir satr esine ihtiyacm yok.
Now for a given link, the color should not be white because the background of the sideDrawer is white,
imdi, verilen bir balant iin renk beyaz olmamaldr, nk yan ekmecenin arka plan beyazdr.
I want to use a brown color here and I will use #8F5C2C,
Burada kahverengi bir renk kullanmak istiyorum ve 8 F 5 kullanacam.
the brown color we used before, text-decoration of course still is none, the height is not
Tabii ki texta yaratlmadan nce hala kullandmz kahverengi rengi hala% 100 deil, en yksekte
100% though but the width is.
deil, ancak genilii grmek iin bakn.
I also want to make sure that box-sizing is border box so we'll leave that
Ayrca, kutu boyutlandrmasnn kenarlk borke olduunu ve bylece brakacamdan emin olmak isterim.
but I don't need the padding,
Ama dolguya ihtiyacm yok.
I don't need the border bottom,
Taban szdrmam gerekmiyor.
this can all go and display can still be set to block though.
Bu hepsi gidebilir ve ekran yine de engellemek iin ayarlanabilir.
Now for active items, I don't want to set the background color to brown,
imdi etkin eler iin arka plan rengini kahverengi yapmak istemiyorum.
I want to set it to this blue color instead, not the background color excuse me, the color,
Bunun yerine rengi grntlemek iin ayarlamak istiyorum, zemin rengi deil, rengimi kandr.
so the text color and I'll get rid of background color and border bottom,
Metin rengi ve arka plan renginden ve snr altndan kurtulacam.
I don't want to have any of that.
Bunlardan herhangi birine sahip olmak istiyorum.
And as always you're of course free to adjust this to a way you find to look nicer.
Ve her zamanki gibi tabii ki daha adaletli grnen bir ekilde adaleti serbest brakmak zgrdr.
So these are my mobile styles,
Bunlar benim Mobot stillerim.
now let's throw out any duplicate styling setups we have in mobile and desktop. For example box-sizing border
imdi mobil ve masast gibi kutu boyutlandrma snr kutusunda sahip olduumuz yinelenen stil ayarlarn
box,
dolandralm.
we already defined this in mobile,
Bunu zaten Mobil'de tanmladk.
we don't need to redefine it here because media queries of course are merged with the original classes
Medya sorgular elbette orijinal maddelerle birletirildiinden burada yeniden tanmlamamz gerekmiyor.
so whatever we set up here is generally capped and then we can override selected properties but block
Dolaysyla, burada ne yaparsak yapalm genellikle kapaldr ve seilen zellikleri geersiz klabiliriz ancak ayn
sizing doesn't need to be overwritten because we want to use the same value.
deeri kullanmak istediiniz iin blok boyutunun zerine yazlmasna gerek yoktur.
I will use the same values here but I'll set the width too auto here to not use the width of 100%
Burada ayn deerleri kullanacam, ancak genilii de ayarlayacam, ancak mobil ayarlarda yaptm
which I did set up in the mobile settings though, I'll also overwrite the other settings,
genilii yzde 100 olarak kullanmayacam, ancak ortalama ayarlar da geersiz klacaktm.
so this looks good to me.
Bu bana iyi geldi.
for a selected link here, I now want to set the color to white
Burada seilen bir balant iin rengi beyaza ayarlamak istiyorum.
so here it is brown,
Yani burada kahverengi.
it should be white for me.
Benim iin beyaz olmal.
Text-decoration is already set up in the mobile settings,
Ak metin dekorasyonu, mobil ayarlarda zaten oluturulmutur.
height and padding, that's important for me.
Benim iin nemli olan ykseklik ve dolgu.
Border bottom is important,
Snr Bawden nemlidir.
box-sizing and display,
Kutu boyutlandrma ve grntleme.
we got that set up here in the mobile settings already so we can get rid of it down here.
Mobil ayarlarda zaten burada ayarladk, bylece buradan kurtulabiliriz.
And for hovering and active links, everything needs to be set up because we have a totally different
Gezinme ve aktif balantlar iin her eyin ayarlanmas gerekiyor, nk mobil uzunluklar
style for mobile links.
iin tamamen farkl bir stile sahibiz.
Let's now save this and have a look at it,
imdi gvende olalm ve bir gz atalm.
it's looking good but they're still sitting next to each other.
yi grnyor, ama yine de birbirlerinin yannda oturuyorlar.
The reason for this is that
Bunun sebebi ld.
our navigation items, the unordered list which wraps the links, there
Navigasyon elerimiz oradaki balantlar sarmalayan bir sipari listesine bakmaktadr.
we're using flexbox
Fluxbox kullanyoruz.
and that leads to the item sitting next to each other by default.
Ve bu enin varsaylan olarak birbirine bitiik olmasn salar.
Isn't a problem, we just need to add a media query here too with min-width 500px
Sorun deil, yalnzca 500 piksel olan dakikayla bir medya sorgusu eklememiz gerekiyor.
and in there, I'll now set up my navigation items class and I will set the flex flow to row here because
kurduk ve esnek ak burada sraya koyacam nk aklda tutmak masast aygtlar iin eit olmam salyor.
keep in mind, this is the media query for desktop devices
Ve u anda benim gezinti eleri snfm
so there they should sit next to each other
Bylece birbirlerinin yanna oturmalar gerekir.
but for mobile devices, I will actually set a new flex flow of column so that they sit beneath each
Fakat mobil cihazlar iin Cullom'un yeni bir Flack ak yapacam, bylece birbirlerinin
other.
altna oturdular.
Now if we save this, we see the items are indeed stacked on top of each other, on bigger screens,
imdi bunu syleseniz, elerin byk ekranlarda birbiri zerine yldn gryoruz.
we still have the old look.
Hl eski grnmz var.
We also get a couple of issues here, by the way the distorted burger when switching is only due to the
Ayrca, bozulduunda Briga'nn anahtarlama ilemi yalnzca geiten kaynaklandndan birka sorunla kar
switching,
karyayz.
once you reload and load the app as the user would see it, it's looking fine, but we got issues here, for
Uygulamay yeniden yklediinde ve yklediinde kullanc gzel grnyor, ancak burada
example the navigation items are also visible on the toolbar on smaller screens
sorunlar var, rnein gezinme eleri ara ubuunda kk ekranlarda grnr durumda.
and of course, that should not be the case,
Ve tabii ki byle olmamal.
I don't want to have the navigation items in the toolbar on small screens,
Navigasyon elerinin ara ubuunda kk ekranlarda olmasn istemiyorum.
I have the sideDrawer for that.
Bunun iin sallamam gerekiyor.
I also want to have a little bit more spacing between the logo and my navigation items here on mobile.
Ayrca mobil cihazda logolu ve navigasyon elerim arasnda biraz daha boluk brakmak istiyorum.
To fix this, I'll go back to my application and there in the sideDrawer where I include the logo and the navigation
ve logoyu eklediim siteye oraya koyun ve ncelikle logonun alt ksmna biraz kenar boluu ekleyin, bylece
items, I'll first of all add some margin to the button on the logo so that we have some spacing to the
altndaki gezinme elerine bir miktar boluk brakacak ekilde navigasyon eleri ekleyin. belki 42 piksel.
navigation items which are below it, maybe 32px
Bunu dzeltmek iin, bavuru formuma geri dnn
so that should look better
Bu yzden daha iyi grnmelidir.
yes.
Evet.
And to remove the navigation items in the toolbar, we actually need to add a new helper css class
Ve ara ubuundaki navigasyon elerini kaldrmak iin aslnda hepsi sarma esine
which I'll adds to the wrapping element. I'll add it
ekleyen yeni bir yardmc C-s S-Snf eklememiz gerekiyor.
and I'll add it in a media query. So this media query will now check if the maximum width is 499px,
Ve hemen bir sorgu ekledim, bylece bu medya sorgusu maksimum 499 piksele sahip olacak ekilde kontrol edecektir.
so if we are on a mobile device. Then I'll add my desktop only css class and there I will set the
Dolaysyla bir mobil cihazdaysak, masastm yalnzca S snf olarak ekleyeceim ve ekran
display to none.
Norm olarak ayarlayacam.
I don't have this class for the default case
Varsaylan olay iin bu snfm yok.
so for devices which are broader than 500px but that basically means that it takes the default
Yani 500 pikoden daha geni olan ancak temel olarak grntleme blou olan ve bu
styling which is display block and therefore it will be visible.
nedenle de kazanlabilir olacak varsaylan stilini kulland anlamna gelen cihazlar iin.
So I only overwrite this for small devices,
Bu yzden yalnzca kk cihazlar iin zerine yazyorum.
now I can use this new class in a toolbar though and can add it here to the nav item, to the nav element.
imdi bu yeni snfa bir ara ubuunda da kullanabilirsiniz ve buraya nav esinin nav esine ekleyebilirsiniz.
I can use classes desktop only
Yalnzca Klaas'n masastn kullanabilirim.
and now on smaller devices, the navigation items should disappear and they do. We see the logo here
Ve kk cihazlarda navigasyon eleri kaybolmal ve burada logoyu greceksiniz.
but I think that looks quite nice so maybe we'll leave that here.
Fakat bence ok gzel grnyor, bu yzden belki burada brakacaz.
Now with that we got a sideDrawer which looks better, it would look even better if you would have a backdrop
imdi daha iyi grnen bir yan ekmecem varsa, zemin olsayd daha iyi olurdu.
and if we could dynamically open and close it.
Ve dinamik olarak ap kapatabilirsek.
These are the steps we'll work on next.
Bunlar, bir sonraki admda atacamz admlardr.